Guide to the Adolph M. Foerster Collection, 1868-1923 CAM.FOER.2015
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Adolph M. Foerster Collection
1868-1923
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Foerster, Adolph M.
CAM.FOER.2015
16 boxes
The Adolph M. Foerster Collection contains manuscripts and printed scores of Foerster's music, articles written by the composer, newspaper clippings concerning the composer (and the performance of his music), photographs, letters, and "notes" in the composer's hand.
Biography
Life
Adolph Martin Foerster was born to German immigrant parents in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on February 2, 1854. His father, Emil Foerster, was a highly regarded portrait painter who painted many of the most well known local figures of the day. His mother, Elise Marie Noll, was a native of Frankfurt and an accomplished pianist. In addition to Adolph, they had one other child, Julius.
Adolph was surrounded by the arts from birth. In addition to his mother's skills, his father was a very gifted amateur musician who sang in church choirs and other choral groups and played the guitar and flute. Adolph received his first piano instruction from his mother and later studied piano and music theory under Jean Manns, a German immigrant who was revered as one of the best local music teachers. In addition to his music training, Foerster attended public school in Allegheny City (now Pittsburgh's North side).
During his teenage years Foerster frequently appeared as a soloist in various piano and vocal recitals. He also attended almost every concert by notable artists given in the Pittsburgh area. From September 1869 until 1872, Adolph was employed at Kleber & Bro, a music store on Wood Street in Pittsburgh's downtown that had been established in 1845 by musician and composer Henry Kleber and his brother. While working for the Klebers, Foerster met many important artists, among them Theodore Thomas who would conduct Foerster's Festival March at the 1893 Chicago World's Fair. Kleber, for his part, was to become the publisher of most of Foerster's compositions.
In September 1872, at the age of eighteen, Foerster left for Germany where he would study at the Leipzig Conservatory. During his three years as a student, Foerster studied theory under E.F. Richter and R. Papperitz, voice under Leo Grill and Adolph Schimon, and piano under Carl Reinecke, E.F. Wenzel, and Theordore Coccius. In addition to his studies, he was present at major musical events such as Anton Rubinstein performing his keyboard works, Brahms's Hungarian Dances, and Liszt's oratorio Christus, the latter two of which were under the composers' own direction.
Foerster also visited with Richard Wagner, which left him with a permanent admiration for his music. Although Foerster's compositional language and style were completely different from Wagner's, he demonstrated some interest in the motif system and, on more than one occasion, used it in his compositions. Foerster also became acquainted with Robert Franz, developing a strong personal relationship with him. In spite of their age of difference of almost forty years, their friendship remained constant through eighteen years of correspondence until Franz's death in 1892.
After graduating with highest honors from Leipzig Conservatory, Foerster returned to America and accepted a professorship at the Conservatory of Music in Fort Wayne, Indiana. A year and a half later, he returned to Pittsburgh and focused his efforts on helping his hometown's musical culture develop.
In 1879, he married Henrietta M. Reineman, daughter of a highly successful banker, investor, contractor, and landowner. They had a daughter, Elsa Thusnelda, and two sons, Robert Franz (named for the composer) and Norman Otto.
Foerster's career demonstrated versatility as a teacher of piano, voice, and composition, as a pianist and conductor, as a writer on music, and as a composer. Around the Pittsburgh area he taught privately and at numerous institutions such as the Western Pennsylvania Female College (now Chatham College), Geneva College, and the Newell Institute for Young Ladies. He served for thirty years as the examiner of graduating students at Seton Hill Conservatory and organized numerous studio concerts for his students. In 1890, he became the ninth life member of the Music Teachers' National Association and in 1894 he was named treasurer of the organization.
As a performer, he directed the Pittsburgh Symphony Society (a precursor of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra) from 1879 to 1881. In 1882, he was elected director of the Musical Union Choral Society, a position that he held for many years. In addition, he often conducted festival orchestras in performances of his own orchestral compositions. As a pianist, he frequently appeared on stage with other artists performing his songs and chamber music.
As a music writer, his influence extended beyond Pittsburgh through contributions to leading music magazines. He was the Pittsburgh correspondent for the New York based publications Musical Courier and American Art Journal. He also wrote a series of lengthy articles on the history of music in Pittsburgh since the colonial period, only the second attempt of its kind and one that would become a lasting contribution for musicologists. These pieces were originally published in 1920 in the Pittsburgh Dispatch, but were later revised and appeared in Musical Forecast, a Pittsburgh-based magazine.
Foerster did not just record Pittsburgh's music history, but actively voiced his opinions on the current state of affairs and remained an aggressive participant in the local music scene. In 1895, along with prominent citizens, lawyers, and members of the Bohemian Club, he initiated a movement for placing a bust of composer Stephen Collins Foster (a friend of Emil Foerster's and a student of Henry Kleber's) in Carnegie Music Hall and building a memorial. He was also a constant advocate of local musicians, musical organizations, performances series, and music libraries.
Foerster's efforts on behalf of the musical growth of his native city were evident in the titles the city bestowed upon him, during his lifetime and after his death in 1927. He was known as "a smoky city's favorite," "the dean of Pittsburgh," and "the composer of the west."
Works
The works of Adolph M. Foerster cover every phase of musical composition but opera. He wrote works for piano, organ, chamber ensemble, solo voice, vocal ensemble, chorus, and orchestra. His complete works number in excess of two hundred and fifty separate compositions.
He often gave his compositions descriptive titles, which were evocative, literary, and loosely programmatic. He avoided the term symphony, and rarely used terms such as sonata, sonatina, and rondo. His exacting musical taste was generally conservative. Permeated with chromaticism and bold modulations, Foerster's music consistently typifies the German Romantic period.
Of all forms, the secular song was his favorite means of expression. The influence of Schubert, Schumann, Brahms, and Franz remained the guiding factor throughout his life. He scorned writing for the public taste, explaining that he was concerned only with how his songs compared with the great romantic Lieder.
The five decades of Foerster's compositional career were highlighted by many memorable events. Throughout the 1880s Foerster's works were played in Germany, France, Holland, and England. The premiere of his Dedication March, commissioned for the opening of Carnegie Music Hall in 1895 and performed by the New York Symphony Orchestra under Walter Damrosch, received attention from national press, marking him as a distinguished American composer. In 1898, Foerster's Prelude to Goethe's Faust won first prize (shared with Fidelis Zitterbart) in a competition sponsored by the Pittsburgh Art Society. On December 30, 1921, Westinghouse Radio aired twelve of his compositions and one year later ran an all–Foerster program, giving the composer his widest public audience yet.
Reputation and Influence
Although Foerster was once a prominent composer and a vital player in Pittsburgh's burgeoning musical scene, he is now a forgotten man. His orchestral works were performed by such orchestras and conductors as the New York Symphony Orchestra under Walter Damrosch, the Cincinnati and Philadelphia Orchestras under Wassilli Leps, and the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra under Victor Herbert, Anton Seidl, and Foerster himself. His compositions were welcomed and accepted for publication by leading American and German publishers and his work received considerable attention in major music journals and newspapers, which praised him for his originality and musicianship.
As early as 1906 Foerster was omitted from the New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians. The only posthumous attention the composer received were a handful of reissues and arrangements of his music from 1940, a 1986 reprint of his Album of Lyrics, Op. 53, a single sound recording that contains only one his songs, "On the Sea," and a 1996 dissertation discussing his life and works.
Scope and Content Notes
The Adolph M. Foerster collection contains manuscripts and printed scores of Foerster's music, articles written by the composer, newspaper clippings concerning the composer (and the performance of his music), photographs, letters, and "notes" in the composer's hand. The different genres of music include, but are not limited to, solo voice (for various voices) and piano, solo voice and orchestra, full orchestra, chamber orchestra, band arrangements, piano arrangements, string quartet, and solo instrument with piano. The manuscripts in the collection are primarily in two different hands, that of Foerster himself and a copyist, Gus Mueller. Several items in the collection (all of which are printed scores and parts) are identical.
Existence and Location of Copies
The Adolph M. Foerster Collection has been scanned but access to the images is only currently available on CDs stored at the Center for American Music.
Acquisition Information
The Adolph M. Foerster Collection was transferred to the Center for American Music from the Theodore Finney Music Library at the University of Pittsburgh in the 1990s.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the follow six series:
Series I. Music Manuscripts
Series II. Printed Music
Series III. Articles, Periodicals, and Newspaper Clippings
Series IV. Photos
Series V. Correspondence
Series VI. Programs
Music -- Manuscripts; Music -- Pennsylvania; Composers -- United States; German Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Foerster, Adolph M. -- Manuscripts
- Music Manuscripts, I.
  - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Content Notes
    holograph score. 23 pages.
  - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: score, 1877 (Box 1, Item 005A)
      Holograph manuscript.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: Piccolo, 1877 (Box 1, Item 005B)
      holograph manuscript, piccolo part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: first and second flute, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004C)
      Holograph manuscript, first and second flute.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: first and second oboe, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004D)
      Holograph manuscript, 1st and 2nd Oboe.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 1st and 2nd Clarinet, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004E)
      Holograph manuscript. 1st and 2nd clarinet part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 1st and 2nd bassoon, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004F)
      Holograph manuscript. 1st and 2nd bassoon part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 1st and 2nd Horn, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004G)
      Holograph manuscript. 1st and 2nd horn.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 3rd and 4th horn, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004H)
      holograph manuscript, 3rd and 4th horn.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 1st and 2nd trumpet, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004I)
      holograph manuscript. 1st and 2nd trumpet.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 1st and 2nd trombone, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004J)
      Holograph manuscript. 1st and 2nd trombone.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 3rd trombone, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004K)
      Holograph manuscript. 3rd trombone.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: tuba, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004L)
      holograph manuscript, tuba part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: Tympani, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004M)
      holograph manuscript, tympani part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: bass drum part, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004N)
      holograph manuscript. bass drum part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: cello, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004O)
      Holograph manuscript. Cello part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 1st violin, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004P)
      Holograph manuscript. 1st violin part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: 2nd violin, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004Q)
      Holograph manuscript. 2nd violin.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: viola part, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004R)
      holograph manuscript. Viola part.
    - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester: bass part, 1877 (Box 1, Item 004S)
      Holograph manuscript. Bass part.
  - Im Rhein, in schonen Strome (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Im Rhein, in schonen Strome, October 30, 1874 (Box 1, Item 003A)
    - Opus 7 Nocturne for the Piano (Box 1, Item 003B)
      Holograph manuscript
    - Ich stand in dunkeln Traumen, May 17, 1874 (Box 1, Item 003C)
  - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Later copy than 6 with corrections in the Bassoon parts. Holograph manuscript. 23 pages.
  - Opus 8 March-Fantasie fur grosses Orchester (Box 1, Folder 8)
    holograph score. 31 pages. heavy board cover with leather title plaque: chord voicing changes from Item 5.
  - Opus 10 Thusnelda (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Holograph manuscript. Cover contains four lines from a poem by Karl Schafer, German script and illegible. 14 pages.
  - Opus 11 Hunting Song (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Holograph score. 1 page. at the bottom is written, "sketch for hunting song, op. 11." The reverse side has other sketches which are crossed out.
  - Opus 15 Fantasie for violin and piano (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Holograph manuscript. 2 pages. Introduction in 6/8 time on top eight lines, 39 measures. Bottom three lines and part of 2nd page an incomplete song. Back page has ten measures of an unidentified song, the rest of the page and opposite side have the 4/4 section of this work, 99 measures in ink.
  - Opus 16 no. 1 Sonatina for the piano (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Holograph score. 4 pages.
    - Opus 16 no. 1 Sonatina for the piano (Box 1, Item 16A)
    - Opus 16 no. 2 Sonatina for the piano (Box 1, Item 16b)
  - Opus 17 no. 2 Melodie, Dec. 16, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Holograph manuscript. Violin and piano. 4 pages.
  - Opus 20 no. 1 Springs verdure and Opus 6 no. 5 Meeresstille, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Holograph score. 2 pages.
    - Opus 20 no. 1 Springs verdure (Box 1, Item 20a)
    - Opus 6 no. 5 Meeresstille, 1875 (Box 1, Item 20b)
  - Opus 21 Quartet fur Violin, Bratsche, Dec. 30, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    score, holograph. violoncello und Klavier. 22 pages. Earliest MS. The second movement appears in a slightly different version than latter MS or printed version.
  - Opus 21 Quartet fur Violin, Bratsche (Box 1, Folder 22)
    score, holograph. violoncello und Klavier. 22 pages. 2nd movement omitted. Bound with heavy cardboard cover and varies with other copies.
  - Opus 21 Quartet fur Violin, Bratsche, March 6, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    score, holograph. violoncello und Klavier. 38 pages. revision copy finished on March 6, 1887. Fourth movement follows the third, the second copied last. This version agrees closely with the printed version.
  - Opus 21 Quartet fur Violine, Bratsche (Box 1, Folder 26)
    score, holograph. violoncello und Klavier. 8 pages. Incomplete, parts of the third and fourth movements.
  - Opus 22 no. 1 The Bedouin's prayer (Box 1, Folder 27)
    holograph. male chorus. 3 p. There is no opus number and title is given in German.
  - Opus 23 Love song, July 17, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Holograph score. 17 pages. Marked as old score. There are many corrections and the first two measures are crossed out. Key of F.
  - Opus 23 Love song, July 17, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Holograph score. 17 pages. some corrections, first two measures intact. Dedication to Miss Dora Hennigen crossed out. Key of E. Flat.
  - Opus 23 Love song (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Holograph score. 5 pages. dedication crossed out.
  - Opus 23 Love song, August 1887 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Holograph score. 7 pages. Inside leaf has twelve measures which later appear as the introduction. Key of E flat.
  - Opus 23 Love song, August 1887 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Holograph score 6 pages. marked as singer's copy. Key of E flat.
  - Opus 23 Love song (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Holograph manuscript. 9 pages. Revised, key of E flat. Bound in soft linen cover with title plate. Singer's copy, introduction included.
  - Opus 23 Love song (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Holograph manuscript. 6 pages. Note at the bottom of the first leaf, "please return to A.G. Goodrich, Box 976, Chicago." Key of E Flat.
  - Opus 23 Love song score and parts (Box 3, Folder 40)
    holograph score and parts. 19 pages.
    - Opus 23 Love song score (Box 3, Item 40a)
    - Opus 23 Love song 1st violin (Box 3, Item 40b)
    - Opus 23 Love song 2nd violin (Box 3, Item 40c)
    - Opus 23 Love song viola (Box 3, Item 40d)
    - Opus 23 Love song cello (Box 3, Item 40e)
    - Opus 23 Love song bass (Box 3, Item 40f)
    - Opus 23 Love song 1st and 2nd flute (Box 3, Item 40g)
    - Opus 23 Love song 1st and 2nd oboe (Box 3, Item 40h)
    - Opus 23 Love song 1st and 2nd clarinet (Box 3, Item 40i)
    - Opus 23 Love song 1st and 2nd bassoon (Box 3, Item 40j)
    - Opus 23 Love song 1st horn (Box 3, Item 40k)
    - Opus 23 Love song 2nd and 3rd horn (Box 3, Item 40l)
    - Opus 23 Love song trombone (Box 3, Item 40m)
    - Opus 23 Love song tympani (Box 3, Item 40n)
  - Opus 23 Love song (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Holograph score. 22 pages. marked as a defective copy in pencil at the top of the first page.
  - Opus 24 Ein Albumblatt fur Violoncello und Klavier (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Holograph manuscript. 4 pages. Proof copy sent to C.F. Kahnt, Leipzig.
  - Opus 25 no. 1 O frage nicht (Box 3, Folder 45)
    holograph score. 3 pages.
  - Opus 25 no. 1 O frage nicht (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Holograph manuscript. 2 pages.
  - Opus 26 Novelette fur Violine and Klavier (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Opus 27 no. 1 Eros (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Holograph score. 1 page. pencil sketch.
  - Opus 29 Trio for piano, violin and violoncello (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Holograph score. 2 pages. Contains 79 measures of which the first 45 generally match later score. Parts not completely filled out. Outside leaf contains a short piano piece which is either a childhood effort or an exercise in the style of Mozart.
  - Opus 29 Trio for piano, violin and violoncello, June 7, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Holograph score. 50 p. Bound with heavy paper cover. Parts, extra, dated April 22, 1892.
    - Opus 29 Trio for piano, violin and violoncello score, June 7, 1891 (Box 3, Item 52a)
    - Opus 29 Trio for piano, violin and violoncello violin, June 7, 1891 (Box 3, Item 52b)
    - Opus 29 Trio for piano, violin and violoncello cello, June 7, 1891 (Box 3, Item 52c)
  - Opus 29 Trio fur Klavier, Violine, und Violoncello (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Holograph score. 6 pages. second movement only
  - Opus 30 no. 3 The daisy, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Opus 31 The falconer, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Holograph score. 59 pages. December 29, 1893 first performance in Scranton, PA. On the inside of leaf two is a poem by Karl Schafer marked "Motto" and divided into three parts. On the first side of leaf three is a list of first performances. 1 complete copy of orchestra score is bound.
    - Opus 31 The falconer: score, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57a)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st violin, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57b)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 2nd violin, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57c)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: viola, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57d)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: cello, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57e)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: bass, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57f)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st and 2nd flute, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57g)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st and 2nd oboe, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57h)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st and 2nd bassoon, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57i)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st and 2nd clarinet, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57j)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st and 2nd horn, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57k)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 3rd and 4th horn, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57l)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 4th horn and trombone, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57m)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st and 2nd trumpet, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57n)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 1st and 2nd trombone, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57o)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: 3rd trombone, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57p)
    - Opus 31 The falconer: tympani, Dec. 29, 1893 (Box 3, Item 57q)
  - Opus 32 Fest Marsch fur grosses Orchester, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Holograph score. 20 pages. Listing of orchestra parts needed on inside cover leaf.
  - Opus 32 Festival March (Box 5, Folder 59)
    Holograph score. 20 pages.
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 1st violin (Box 5, Item 59a)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 2nd violin (Box 5, Item 59b)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: viola (Box 5, Item 59c)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 1st clarinet (Box 5, Item 59d)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 2nd clarinet (Box 5, Item 59e)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 1st bassoon (Box 5, Item 59f)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 2nd bassoon (Box 5, Item 59g)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 1st horn (Box 5, Item 59h)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 2nd horn (Box 5, Item 59i)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 3rd horn (Box 5, Item 59j)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 4th horn (Box 5, Item 59k)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 1st trumpet (Box 5, Item 59l)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 2nd trumpet (Box 5, Item 59m)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 1st trombone (Box 5, Item 59n)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 2nd trombone (Box 5, Item 59o)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: 3rd trombone (Box 5, Item 59p)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: tuba (Box 5, Item 59q)
    - Opus 32 Festival March: score (Box 5, Item 59r)
  - Opus 32 Festival March, May 12, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    Holograph score. 10 pages. title page has the inscription, "Festival march for full orchestra, written for the opening of the May Festival, Pittsburgh, Pa. Tuesday, May 12, 1891. Anton Seidl, conductor."
  - Opus 32 Festival March (Box 5, Folder 61)
    Holograph score. 10 pages. bound with heavy paper cover and gamble hinge: Same hand as 60A: Later version (includes corrections)
  - Opus 33 Quartet, Dec. 25, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    Holograph manuscript. 41 pages. Inside cover page has a newspaper clipping covering the first performance on Dec. 30, 1891.
  - Opus 33 Quartet, June 8, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    Holograph manuscript and parts. bound with heavy paper cover. Also extra parts unbound.: Collection includes an additional copy of the third mmovement for all 4 parts.: copied by Gus Mueller: Earlier version of 310A, also copied by Gus Mueller: minor changes only???
    - Opus 33 Quartet: 1st violin, June 8, 1894 (Box 5, Item 65A)
    - Opus 33 Quartet: 2nd violin, 1894 (Box 5, Item 65b)
    - Opus 33 Quartet: viola, 1894 (Box 5, Item 65c)
    - Opus 33 Quartet: cello, 1894 (Box 5, Item 65d)